h what else? But
still you can hear that's
all. Okay, Anand we'll get started because people are
Okay, cool.
Let's dive in then. And like before, it'll be good
if you otherwise good if you interrupt with questions as
much as you can because it's one way of staying
awake.
inform but I'll also stay in the stages so that if anyone has any
question I will ask what that question is and I will relay on the computer to
Sure. Thank
you.
awake and listening
No, not for me to stay awake uh or me to get
feedback but I had a a
classmate senior classmate who was doing his PhD uh while
I was doing my MBA. uh he was at that time the finance secretary of
the current government and uh he would periodically
ask questions and of course class participation is
rewarded literally with marks but in his case
he said I ask questions more to stay awake in class because if
I don't ask questions I will fall
asleep
Okay. One second.
Sure. Yeah.
uh Bluetooth connection.
Yeah.
about rocker
strength.
Rocker rocker trans is this one.
Huh?
I can still hear you. But
if I'm speaking, am I better
audible? Okay,
great. Wonder.
Cool. Can I just uh briefly recap which is please
ask questions if nothing else the class will go in the direction that you want
rather than some random direction that I will be taking it in.
But there are four broad themes that I'm planning to
talk about today which will relate to some of the material that you have seen
before. The first is that tools
are going to be shaping visualizations like they used to
uh when William player was creating his
visualizations. They were more handdrawn. Uh and that meant that there
was more variety, more flexibility, fewer people could create it. Then
we had the Excel era where standardized charts became more the
norm and uh therefore more people could do stuff
but there was lesser variety in charts
that used to come out with AI
creating more visual formats. These days we have a lot more
of the kinds of visual variety that
we used to see before and can probably start seeing more.
I'll show a few of the visualizations that I saw recently that
I thought were interesting and
were created by people with varied levels of visualization experience
which I think is the main point. I'll start
with a visualization called Jev's
keep. Some of you may have heard of this model called
Jev J V. a lot of
buzz around it in recent times. It's a relatively inexpensive
model unlike say the likes of chart GPT etc which generate
text. It can only say yes or no or choose between
categories or generate a number but it's pretty
fast. So one of my colleagues uh who is fresh
out of college um he took Jeb
and started doing uh security
screening that is when a request comes to a
website. Can we check if it is an SQL injection
attack? Can we check if it is a path traversal kind of
okay not able to presume it makes it worse. uh but on
the right side you may be able to see uh
the different categories of attacks. the way
he implemented it. I have no idea if it was uh intentional
or just a a model choice but I think there
must have been some intention behind it where he
encoded each of these as little dots that is every request that's coming in as a little dot
going through a casle and as the requests come in
if they are a security act they get added to the
tally board on top effectively creating a
dynamic bar chart trace. Now
a he's not familiar with bar chart
traces. It emerged as part of the discussion that he was having with the
model. The whole concept of a castle again uh just
emerged and the dynamic uh streaming
of course this I can and should
accelerate. Let me just play it at 5x speed.
uh came in because of a discussion that we had saying look let's run this as
a simulation so that people can see what's happening
pretty interesting now a lot of people have in the
recent times asked me oh what is this kind of animated visualization that
you use and I think that's this was recently in a trip
to Manila where uh they were not as
familiar with animated visualizations as they were with uh
Excel visualizations Today that's so much
more a possibility than it used to be that people are just using it left, right
and center. Why not? Why does visualization have to be
static when the medium that we are using these days
can support dynamic formats? Let's
take another visualization. This uh was created
by a Japanese student in his first year of uh college from
city university of Tokyo. The interesting part of the
visualization this is a broader story
but this was for uh
I forget which football series this is but he
effectively created a heat map of where the goals
were successfully scored from
and bunch of variations around this to see
where individual uh specific spots from where
each individual goal was stored. Um, with the ability
to look specifically at at what time who scored which
goal and animated right down to the point of
the individual uh goal position
and each one of these goals step by step walking
through what exactly happened. So if
then this goal so this was potentially the origin they don't
have the origin data but this was probably the origin this is the record short
position and it moved in here.
Oh, I need you saying
something. Okay, maybe not.
Uh the idea here is that uh
uh heat map of football goals is not
something that
uh Oh. Oh,
okay. I don't think I've changed anything in the mic, but I'll get a
little closer in any case. Is it okay
now? Okay, fine. I'll just continue
this way then. Now, it's not that uh
heat map kind of a visualization is particularly
difficult if you knew D3, but this is a student who knows no
program and I think that's becoming the second kind of
uh capability. uh unleash
that's happened. What that means is that some
of those who are artistically inclined or have a
strong domain sense, they probably have a bit of
an edge in creating visualizations
because this student obviously knows football and says,
"Oh, look, this is how I want to see it." And
the tool ceases to be a constraint because now you just tell it to do something and it can do
it. It almost becomes the question now
becomes then do you have a good enough story to tell and do
you have an interesting way of telling those stories?
Some of these stories emerge just from the domain itself. For instance,
u one that uh we've been sharing with
uh the uh times of India is
on environmental change insights. Uh I'm not sure if I
showed this last time but if so it'll be great if someone could just let me
know and I'll go a little faster. But what we did
was looked at satellite imagery and zoomed
in into specific uh areas comparing.
So let's take Chennai. I'm going to
u zoom out of Chennai a little
bit. And what you have here
in these little grids is how
much water is retreating or drying.
So green means water coverage has increased, red means
water coverage has decreased between 2015 to
2025. So effectively if I take the map as
it was in 2015 compare it with the map as it is in
2025 for each of those little I think 100 m by
100 m grids we used a vision model
specifically a geospatial vision model called ALMO
earth to see what is the water coverage before what is the water coverage
now and create a heat map of where in
Chennai water has water bodies have grown and where they
have shrunk. So, for instance, uh let's look at one of
these hotspots here. Zooming
in. Oh, you aren't even seeing the screen.
Sorry. Let me do this again.
Uh apologies. I will start
again. So, that's Chennai's water coverage uh or
water difference. So this is Chennai in 2015
and this is
uh Chennai satellite imagery. Now if we take
Almo Earth's evaluation of in each 100 m
by 100 m grid how much water coverage there was
before versus now. The greens are where there is more coverage.
Let me zoom in into one of these spots which should be
pretty easily recognizable. But is it I mean uh
is can anyone name what this bright
green spot is likely to
bright green spot. What is it likely to
be? It's
water. But where is it?
Oh, no. I'm asking if anyone
could guess what that green strip
ah green they said greenery but yeah in the discussion it
was. Huh? Correct.
But let me put it this way. Does anyone know Chennai well enough to know where this
water ah where where this could be the
is exactly?
Yeah. river. Correct. And if we uh just take a
look at uh this
is the current situation and uh this is
what it used to be. Now uh the fadedness
of the image is not what it's using as a metric. The amount of water
itself which you may be able to see from the uh edges has grown
more in this area. But of course you could also say it's because there is more
water for it to grow. But still the Adar River has certainly become
a lot uh wetter. Uh and
there are other spots like let's just randomly pick one
of these um where
okay there is more water coverage probably
some northern part of kuam or whatever uh which
used to be a lot drier uh no not ku
probably the northern part of mingham canal of some such thing u
that is a lot better and similarly we can look at this from a
vegetation perspective effective as well. uh or greenery
as you looked at to see where greenery is growing, where greenery is
shrinking very simple heat map visualization but the underlying data is
changing yet another kind of uh visual
representation that I'm finding a lot more of these days is uh
sands so uh this is a research
report that uh is based on McKenzie's uh global
energy perspective report they've been publishing about
27 of these very detailed reports
every here and those reports
what uh we've done was taken every single fact in
it and broken it down saying that look there are
a total of about 2,200 odd
facts each of these is one such so
here one of the facts that or claims let's say that they have put in
is power sector gas demand in
2035 will be less than 100 BCM because renewables are going to be
more competitive. Some statement of fact and each one of these
is one. The nice part is that it was
easy for the audience to see uh how
many facts did we get by year? What types
of facts do we have? So lots of forecasts, relatively fewer
estimates, sub 230 odd facts, some
169 causalities, etc. Which ones should we watch
more of? Which ones should we watch less of? What are the
kinds of reports that these facts are presented? So getting
a map of what is there and where it is
becomes easier and that sort of a thing can be used in a variety
of different areas. For instance, in product management.
So uh this is uh for
a company called Optum. Optum is
a media
we still looking at the uh the water map or is there a different map that
research. I'm sorry. Uh I will start again.
My apologies. I will yeah consciously
switch tab to tab and seeing different screens. So let me do
this again. Uh
this correct
exactly. So the McKenzie uh global energy
perspective report has about 27 of these
publications and each publication was broken
down into about 2,200 claims. So one of
these is a claim that says under accelerated renewables
uh etc are projected to plateau after 2020.
They're making a forecast of this kind like this. There
are more than 2,000 of these which it
becomes easier for people to get a sense of
uh you know get a map off so to speak by
saying by year we seem to have a lot more of these claims in
2024. Um there are many more forecasts
than estimates than facts than
causalities. The ones that we need to watch for high probability or
I importance there are about 1250 of those where
they occur across the reports. And of course if you say look
just tell me in which report are there things that I should watch and sort
by that um or even let's say color by that
it becomes easy to track groups of claims
across different categorizations. This is a characteristic of
the sandance kind of uh visual animations. We
have seen that these are not well Excel
creatable charts at the very least. Certainly D3 creatable
charts which is limited to a smaller audience but almost all of these
were created by people who were not able to create visualizations
but knew the domain. Let me switch to another one. Share the
tab before I forget. Um another visualization
was created for uh company
Optum to show their product portfolio. Again a very simple uh
sandance kind of a visualization that said look you have about
uh 28 products uh
that are documented and they belong to a whole bunch of these
categories and they fit into these
workflows. So rather than think of a
product being a monolithic whole, think of it as it is
delivering some capabilities. These capabilities are focused
in specific areas. What you need to do is maybe rationalize it in a
slightly different way. If you look at what are the key common
areas that you should be focusing on. There are some products that are emerging
right in the middle of these capabilities. Therefore, maybe you should focus on
rationalizing those. Here are some external dependencies where
you're dependent on a competitor. So maybe watch out either buy that
competitor out or remove that dependency are examples
of somewhat more novel visualizations that I've seen
in the last month or so. Again, almost all
created by people with a strong understanding of the
domain and a relatively weak understanding of
visualization or technology. what am
I therefore leading towards? Um you've
seen in this course that the over history
uh at different points when technologies became
available the shape of visual representations changed.
Today, today over the course of the last few years
and the next few years, we are at another one of those inflection points.
to treat what you're studying
from a tools perspective with a little bit of skepticism. The
tooling is changing rapidly and what you're learning from a
technique and a history perspective with a little higher
importance. The lessons both of history and the principles that
we learn might last a little longer. And
one of the principles that we are talking about
is how well do models see
things or sorry how well do people see things. graphical perception. We
have our own set of biases.
We are able to spot differences in uh color,
even subtle shades. When they're right next to each other, but
move them a little further away, surround them by other colors, we totally get
confused. Length perception is pretty good.
Area perception is not uh perhaps as good. Angular perception
is pretty bad. When we start things near each other,
we are able to see smaller differences further apart. It
becomes trickier. These are the kinds of mistakes we
make. But now with
agents coming in, agents are increasingly a
consumer of our visualizations as well. What I mean by that
is okay half the time when somebody sends
me a presentation which probably has a bunch of charts I just
uploaded to chart GPT tell me what they're seeing
now that will contain a chart ultimately chart GPT is that's going to be
reading the chart if you are going to be creating visualization you may as well make
sure that cloud or charge GPT or Pacity or whatever is going to be consuming the
chart for probably half the audience can read it as
Of course, you could put it in the text, too. That is a good thing. But
there are likely a set of things that
LLM are better able to
visualize uh when shown as a picture or is just almost impossible
to convey as images, right? So,
what how do LLM see and what are their
biases? That's something that's probably worth
exploring as well. So, let's take a look. We were
playing around with a few benchmarks. I'm shifting to a
bookshelf benchmark. One of my colleagues, again, fresh out of
college. He uh took a bunch of
photos and uh here is an example
of one of the photos he took. It's of a bookshelf.
and asked a series of models, can you tell me
all the books that are there in this particular bookshelf?
A, B, C, etc. Manually classified all of those. Some of those, like the
first two are relatively easy. again. see the
titles clearly and completely. Some of them are harder like the last two
where they're both messy, not very visible,
etc. and created a benchmark.
The benchmark was the prompt was fairly
straightforward. It is list all the books and he compared the books against
the results and the results are
interesting. There were a couple of uh uh runs that
he made and looking at the overall
F1 score. What we're finding is couple
of things. Uh the newer models especially the anthropic
models Opus 5.5 and Sonnet 5.5 is a
way ahead of the latest Gemini models which is not not
way bit ahead. um 86%
is what opus 5.5 scored with high effort as compared to
sonnet 5.5 uh which was at 80% and Gemini 3.8
flash scored 70%. In other words able to
get more than half the books right but not
uh none of the models could get all of the books
right. Fair enough. Now that tells us a couple of things. one
that there are models that can see better that are there are models that
can see worse. The second in each of these cases he tried
it with low effort as well as with high effort and the models have the
tunable parameters. So you can literally tell them look a little closer.
She'll just tell me what you see. And in many cases
the uh high effort outperformed the low
effort. Not always. For let's say Luna, if you actually asked
it to look harder, it did worse. Happens.
Um if you tell Gemini to look harder,
it doesn't really have much of an improvement. But with Sonet, there was a
decent improvement. The other factor is how much is this going to
cost. Now on this chart, the x-axis
is how much it cost. Yaxis is
how accurate it was. You can see that the more expensive models tend to be
more accurate or vice versa. You pay for a certain degree
of accuracy. Put another way,
unlike humans where you say I have an audience,
the audience has to read it. You now have to start factoring
in does the person whom I'm going to
send a visualization to have a model that's going to read
it? If so, do they have a better model? Do they have a worse
model? How is that model or what are
the biases that that model has that I should factor in
start becoming a question? Incidentally,
uh the person who built it, Atarva, he uh chose to use
an interesting visual representation for the uncertainty
in the cost. Uh you see that the
cost has a horizontal bar. The reason is when I
asked him look what is the cost of uh each of these he
said oh I didn't measure it okay you have the chats
right go back and uh do a measurement
he said the charts are there but I don't have
the uh reasoning uh text
that is hidden by uh chart GPT so I don't actually have
the full reasoning tokens I can probably do an estimate
You could create user model, have it go through the
transcript and run similar uh
uh run a similar process again, see if you can measure it
and put in an uncertainty estimate. So this
is an uncertainty estimate by a
model of a model's cost and the
range varies. So for instance for set the range is relatively
narrower for Luna the range of cost estimates is much wider because we have far
less uh understanding of how much it thinks and we'll
come to this uncertainty bit and how we handle it in a short
life but where I want to go with this is that
models are reading charts
models have different abilities to read
charts and there may also be a certain
amount of bias in doing
this. Let's look at what we know about
the models biases. There is a
benchmark called chat, sorry, chart QA
pro. It's on GitHub. And what the team
that put this together did was they took a series of questions.
Let me open one of
these. Okay, just going to make this
table here.
So for instance uh the first uh
chart of the eight that you see here is an
image with a question calculate the total percentage of deals made by
buyers from USA, Japan and Singapore combined with an
answer 17. Our charts are
models able to figure this out is what chart QA was
evaluating and the evaluation results are in
here. Um, not sure how well you can hold
on. Okay. Yeah,
this probably about as big as I can make it, but I'll just summarize
by saying there are some models that do a good job. some models that do a poor
job. But what is perhaps more interesting
is is there a bias? Meaning, do some
models um really get the question right,
really get uh some questions wrong, etc.
Nobody seems to have published a paper based on that. So I said I told
Chad GPT about an hour ago, look um what I want
you to do is download that data
set that yeah I want you to download
uh chart QA pro and answer the question what are the
different kinds of charts or questions that models typically get
wrong? What does that tell us about their perception? Do different models
have different kinds of weaknesses and strengths? Why don't you do the
research and give me a story about it? And here is the story
that it's given me which I'm looking at for the first time. I haven't uh seen this
so far. And it's saying a model can
know what calculation to do but still misread the
picture that it is calculating from. So here
is one question for this picture. When does the wind
capacity first exceed 100 gaw? Okay, I'm
not sure if you can answer that question, but let me try. Um, I have to
look at this green thickness and see when it um
exceeds 100 W. And I think my answer is never.
U but it
says, okay, the thickness I'm just measuring by hand. My thought
would have been never but the
okay ground proof is
203738. Oh, okay. Fine. I should have looked at it cumulatively. Then all of that
was ruined. I misread that chart. And 20 37 38
is yes. When it hits the 100 mark
and 2.5 said
2024 or 5 2.5, a larger
model said 2035. And yet another model said
20334. At least the larger models seem to be roughly in the
ballpark. Fair enough.
What?
Huh?
H
exactly. And
I assume that the thickness or the height of the green
is the wind. But it turns out that
it's asking for the height from the bottom, not just the green part,
which is my mistake. But
uh yeah, the model
seem to have done better than me in any case for
here and I'm just trying to see uh okay
this what are the kinds of mistakes that they are
making the cleanest perception signal is
approximation I see
okay so uh if the
question contains words like approximate, estimate
or roughly then the models
need to infer a number rather than just a copy
of the printed label and that kind of
inference they seem to be doing much worse at so
if what this is saying is look at least if you look at chart
QA one of the principles is don't ask the
reader the model in this case to infer something from the
chart print the number there directly otherwise they do a bad job
of frankly this is something that I tell all of
my team members anyway never have the user
infer a number just show it there that's reflected for
models as well
visual density uh
so what it's saying is okay the denser the
picture. Okay, I'm
not even able to figure out what it's saying.
Uh h okay, this is a good
comparison of how models compare with
humans. And we know the Cleveland and you probably remember the Cleveland and
McGill uh experiments where people were looking at how well
uh humans do on comparing
positions uh which are in a common scale non-aligned
etc.
And it's interesting that the models seem to have a
similar perceptual gap. I'm going to go through
this and probably come back with a more detailed understanding.
But uh the two things that I wanted to share are
a models have their own biases. They may be similar,
they may be different, but they
also are part of the audience now and we may as well get
familiar with the kinds of mistakes they make. That's the second
uh point. A
model AI is able to create visualizations. That's going to change the shape
of the visualizations. Therefore, focus more on technique than
tools. Two, AI is going to be the audience for your visualizations.
So understand them not just as a tool but as an audience that will consume your
visualizations as well. That's going to make a
difference. These were the first two of the four things that I'm planning to
cover. But let me pause here. Any comments,
Any questions,
comments? If no question, we
questions. Okay, then let me ask a question. Open
question. What does this mean? As a result of this, what are you going to do about
it?
Now, what does this mean for you? What we have discussed so far, what are you going to
do about
it? No. No. What does this mean? Me
E. Sorry. What does this
imply?
Yeah. No, no, not meaning as uh
What? Okay. Got it. Got it. What does it mean for you? Okay.
Okay. What are you going to do about this now that I've randomly said a couple of
things? What will you do with this
information?
including uh going and looking at some benchmark information
and generating these observations. Right.
So how do you reflect upon that? that
may not be the correct word. Uh how you use
it or how might this reflect upon your work that I
Yeah,
exactly. What are the Exactly. What is the point of
learning if you're not going to do something about
it?
that throughout the course. We have been asking this question again and again. So
the question was
that you know once again you're able to
No, if you could summarize that would be
great. Thank
you.
thing which you brought out was that it is becoming easy for each of us to kind of use the
LLM and visualize in the way we want. That
was the uh first uh you know thing which you
kind of tried to convey to us. But the second thing is that
whatever LLM will rather generate for each of us. Are we going to bank upon the same
thing or are we going to analyze further? And that analysis can only
be done if if and only if uh we know how
are they rather trying to see the material
or generate the charts in some sense. If I'm on the right
um in
uh got you interestingly I would frame that
differently the second part and we'll come back to the first the second is
saying when you create a
visualization and you send it to somebody They are not
going to open it. They're going to update upload it into their
chart GPT and their chart GP is going to see the
Okay. So, one model is rather creating and the other model is
being uh evaluating the output of the first
visualization. Exactly. So the
model has to understand the visualization and you've
aptly summarized what I've said. My question
is and you're welcome to answer it or anyone else is welcome to join
you but so what are you going to do about
It's totally a
subjective because now everybody wants so much of stuff in so little
time. We would rather try to compete with our
own uh people who are there around us and try to match what
is going on in the world. The first is the survival whether
we are able to survive or not and after we are very certain that
we'll survive the competition. Then comes what are we really going
to you know kind of uh add from our
perspective. So as of now what I'm saying is that we are just trying to survive that is the
which is
doing it I will do it but to an extent till the time you know
I'm stable. So once I'm table then I'll start asking next question
like what it is going to give to me is really good is it really
important.
Got you. Any
anyone else any thoughts based on what we've
covered? How are you going to apply
Any other
it?
Uh, no additional
I'll
wait. Sometimes it's worth
he's he's unlike me. He says I will
pushing.
used. I mean there's a beautiful stuff that he showed in the first right that the
G keep uh I don't know what is the
underlying model that goes behind it but it is like real time monitoring
so real time the the dynamic chart also keeps changing. uh
this is one of the major stuff for instance if you're doing IoT any
manufacturing stuff it's not about static data it's about there is
components are coming in machines are running and you'll have to monitor this on an
online stuff real time okay or marketing analytics for
instance is real time so many of these things stock market many of these things are
actually you want real time graph and not static graphs so
I thought that was I I don't know the model I just saw that you keep
first time any show today. So to me I think that's one
thing that but then that was just the visualization part
but uh if we use the interpretation
engine you know that is one application that the whatever the
last discussion might be relevant to me in that
completely now. Got your take away. Let's also hear from
some
but right so
what are we going to do right so he's sort of
students. I got the question.
Yeah, correct.
That is my question to you.
Paraphrasing exactly the question.
Correct. No,
no. Fair
point. Okay. Okay, tell us tell us more,
please. Go on. Go on.
Maybe you could just come over to the mic and I'll hear
Okay. So, he's asking that's it. He says that's
it. That's all his point is accuracy.
better. Got you. Which is a fair point, right? That is a practical
implication. Any
others?
right.
Please and I
introduce my own bias when I say what you have. So
yeah, I mean what I understood from all this is that uh it can save
our time. I can give all the visualization and everything but at the end what we are going to do is
we are the ones who will be deciding on whether to uh completely rely on it
or like how we go about the
True. And because of that,
what do you think you would want to do
differently? Yeah. So, what will you do
differently?
Um I mean uh maybe assessing
the answers which it gave or yeah basically
optimizing.
Got you. Thank you. I'm learning something
uh from this class actually. Whole bunch of things.
Uh, one of my major takeaways
is and now that I reflect on my classroom and my friends
was a student sitting in a lecture as well,
the mode of learning uh for
many of us. Oh actually I I should frame
this differently. For many years, I
have been learning stuff because I wanted to do something. I have a
problem. I will go learn how to solve the
problem. That makes sense. In your case, you have a problem.
You have an exam to crack. So, you're kind of using one
technique which is sitting in the classroom and figuring out
how to solve it. Obviously, you don't really know what of what I'm going to say is going to come
in what exam or whatever. I find
that half the time, most of the time when
I don't know why I'm learning something, I learn a lot
less. So, I usually just walk out of
uh any place where I don't know why I'm in that
room. You are in less fortunate
situation. You probably at least for attendance got to have to sit in
there. But I have one degree of
freedom which is the at least the second half of this
class I can choose
to answer what you want to know rather
than me telling you what I think you should know because you won't understand why I
think you should know that and it's hard for me to communicate
but if you say look I want to know this I can
answer I'll Sir, that at least will be a
more how they put it. At least
you will get the answer to something that you want to know rather
than knowing something that you don't even know you want to
know. So, let's flip this around at least 15
minutes pure Q&A. What would
you like to know about? And we'll talk about that. I'll share from what I've
learned.
And in case the audio wasn't clear or I was just
rambling summary at next 15
minutes any questions related to visualization and AI that
you
He's he's flipping the set setup now. So
he delivered some stuff. He asked you questions.
Now I don't know from our end we may have an opinion
about it. So what he says is he's turning the tables now and then he
says you first raise the questions and accordingly I will
set up the class. That's what he
says. This is like absolutely
open right it can be any question on visualization. It need not be what he covered
today. It could be something that we have seen in the last six seven weeks or it
could be any anything in that sense related to
visualization or uh um
AI or in the intersection of AI and
and think about how it will help you. Please be
selfish in your questions. No point asking random I
mean don't feel pressurized to ask a question and it could
be why should I care is a valid question.
couldn't hear.
Yeah, I just asked him to come over. Yeah. Is
it compulsory that we need to entirely know the problem definition
Oh, great question.
Uh let me rephrase that. Do I need to know the problem
before I start visualizing something? Depends
very often on who needs a
visualization. In practice, every
dashboard that I've seen is created by someone who
has no idea what they trying to visualize. They don't know the
problem. It is also requested by someone who doesn't know the problem.
Here is a typical sequence. There is
a business owner
typically senior leader who says I want to understand and
he will give a list of why is my uh operations
falling which of my machines are likely to fail in the next 3 months.
He'll give 10 questions like this. Who
is project manager? The project manager will
understand 20% of those questions, write it
down and then give it to a vendor. He'll say I will
create an RFP and the RFP will say I want to be
able to answer 10 such questions and 30 more
of any kind. This will be picked
up by somebody on the sales team
of some company. Let's say the group uh uh who knows
nothing about operations, who knows nothing about
data visualization no but has a
kota they will write a proposal saying here is how we will deliver the
dashboard which will be reviewed by the project manager executed
by a developer who doesn't understand operations who does not necessarily
understand data visualization but knows powerba or tablet or
excel or whatever and after
a whole series of rounds of QA they will produce 20 charts
the business user will say I don't understand head or tail of it. What
rubbish project manager will say no they don't understand it. The developer will say okay I'll
create 30 more charts. Okay look if I take this part of
this chart and I put in this part from here
then I might be able to answer at least one out of my 10
questions but and then the project the business owner's
boss will say you spent half a million dollars already right are
you getting value for it? What is the business owner going to
say? Yeah, yeah, yeah. I've got the answer to at least one of my questions. Okay,
project has been a success. Now, in this
chain, most of the people did not know the
problem definition before they started visualizing
something. They were given a statement, they tried to adhere to
it. In contrast, some people are creating
visualizations that they want to see or are testing
against users. For example, the newsroom of
uh of the New York Times or
the editor has an excellent idea of what the
general public will understand. They will
tell the uh graphics team, create it like this. Make this
change. Iterate, iterate, iterate. sitting literally on their head because the
timeline is what a few hours before they
publish something. In that case, it's
still the graphics designer does not need to
know what the problem is, but the editor is sitting right next to them. The
editor knows and or the journalist, whoever.
But that is a slightly different kind of situation. Same thing happens
with let's say scientific American or springer
nature some of the popular scientific publications or the
economist where again they uh the person creating the visualization
is sitting very close to the person who understands what the audience
needs so still works. The third is the
citizen data scientist or the analyst or
whoever who says look I have a problem. I want to buy a
laptop. I need the maximum features and the lowest
cost. I will plot it. I will see which is on the top left or top right and buy
it. There you know exactly what you want. Or last time when I
showed you my internet movie database chart, right? Rating. things versus
votes. I know exactly what I want. Put another
way, most of the time if you're creating stuff for
yourself, it's important that you should know what you want. But even if you
don't, you can iterate on it. Otherwise, have somebody close to you who knows the
problem definition. Well, in reality, 90% of
visualizations today are created by people who don't know the uh the problem definition. You
can still make a living out of it. Did that answer the question?
I will assume
closer to the
concerned yeah he he's coming so for any
data visualization to take place the first assumption is that there is some
data and there is going to be a question that is going to be asked to him or he can himself
mic. Um,
that there should be data usually true. that there should be a
question usually not true most dashboards
are basically saying I don't know what question can be asked you should be able to answer any
question I'm not saying there shouldn't be a question and you're saying in
practice most data visualizations are created not to answer
a specific question but to satisfy
somebody but I'm still I I suspect I've still not answered your question so go on
push
what are you really asking
uh the problem is also in trying to understand what
kind of data are you going to visualize because there is so varied
kinds of data as of today like you showed that the text can also
be kind of visualized the satellite imagery can be
visualized and you know the normal data the numbers as such can be visualized
So like how do you really hold on to a very
got
you which is a slightly different question. I'll reframe it this
way. I don't exactly know what I want but I am the
audience. I have some data. There are many ways of visualizing it.
How would I go about it? That's part of what you're learning in
this course. Uh
supposing you see 50 different
kinds of visualizations and you take a closer look at
them. You get a sense of okay, tomorrow I can use this. Very
similar to cooking. You've
tasted 50 dishes and you say, "Oh, I
kind of like this. I kind of like that." At least you'll be able to
pick dishes next time. Or if you've prepared a
dish, you know that adding this ingredient makes it taste
slightly this way. The next time you'll be able to
cook much easier. So, how does one go
about knowing um how we
visualize data and what problem uh can be
solved to trying out a variety of different techniques. You don't have to be the one
who does all of it. Meaning to be a good cook, you don't
have to cook every dish. You certainly ought to taste a lot of dishes
and cook a few. So see as many
visualizations as you can of different types.
And by see I don't mean you necessarily need to spend
more time looking for visualizations.
The current time that you spend looking for visualizations look a little
carefully and ask the question how can I use
this? Which is exactly the question I was asking earlier. I showed a bunch of
stuff. If you ask how can I use this?
The time that you spend looking at the visualizations will help you
more. That to me is probably the easiest.
So I'll summarize my answer as
um when you spend time
with creating or seeing visualizations,
ask yourself how is this helping me or how will it help me
in the future? So that when you create your own, you will find it
easier.
Wait
for internet issue to get
resolved.
Yes, I can. Am I
us? Yes. Yes. So, I'm sorry the the
wireless dropped. You are on data right now, but uh let me just make sure. Yeah.
audible? No, is where did uh students lose
me? No,
sorry. Uh, what was I last saying that they
a
heard?
Kumar is trying to log in.
Santos, is it
you? I'm sorry. Okay.
Uh what was he trying to answer and uh where did we got
Yeah. What is the last that you that
Sorry was trying to enter the same meeting. So I
any more the marrier? Let
them join. What do we
lose? Whatever it is, let them
Yeah. What was he answering? He he was
answering his question on you know should I know that what type of
data to you connect and what what what is to be plotted and all that. He
said something like a cookie choice and all that. Today you could you
will be able to generate graphs. That that is where we sort of got disconnected
join. Okay. Okay. Uh oh. Then I have to re
which is probably about so the internet hung
for couple of minutes. Got it. Fine. I'll just
summarize then by saying that when you are looking at any
visualization uh think about how you can
apply whatever you are seeing. That
way when in the future you want to create a visualization
you will know what works, what doesn't work, what techniques might
be relevant and so on. You don't have to spend
more time studying visualizations but you have to
spend the the time that you spent on visualizations more
uh towards learning how to use it rather
than just looking at it.
other question. Yes. Yeah.
Yeah. Come
come. Hello sir. Um so my question is about
LLM can generate a visualization or some plots
and then it can interpret also but it may or may not correct
uh the interpretation s may or may not correct. So is there
any validation technique is there because it can give the plot it can give the
trends but how can I believe it's accuracy accuracy of
Thank you. Now I will go to the third part
of what I was going to cover because this is said but
question to you. Uh I will share something. How will
you use
the data to the ll and try to uh
it?
interpret the plot. So this is the way I can
H okay. And how will that help you? That's the you're saying this is what I will
do. Okay. What is the benefit of knowing um the answer to
your question which is
uh the data and what kind of decision I can make from
the interpretation. So this is the one way I can do
uh still weak. But that's I mean not a
judgment. What I'm saying is that uh if you had
a clearer idea of your question,
the answer will land more strongly. But I'm still going to go ahead and give you
an answer to a related question perhaps.
Let's see where that goes. But I would love for you and
anyone else uh to answer a specific question which
is so how are you going to use what I'm just sharing.
Um let's start maybe
with a few well let's
start my screen should be uh visible
right okay um so one of the things that I
did a short while ago was have an
LLM take an engineering
drawing and asked it now can you create a CAD diagram out of
It
tried. This was given to Codeex. The only
information that it was given was this
uh drawing. Frecad is the software that
it had access to and it uh had
the ability to run a render command. So first it did all kinds of things.
It said I will look at this uh image closer. I will
uh do some cropping of the image. I
will try out other tools etc. Then it gave
up and then next attempt it said okay I'm going to
generate this image. Now this actually
looks uh pretty much like the drawing. The interesting
thing is that it passed all of its own tests.
It said I will write a series of tests to make sure that it is same as the
drawing. I will check if what I've drawn passes those
tests and if it does then agreed. If not, I will keep iterating
until it does. And it built a path
that against the
drawing. If I were to look at it, I would probably say, "Huh, this kind of looks like
that. I'm not sure I know much
better." But it looked at it closer and said, "No,
I'm not happy with this." Um, it said the support
uh is a 48 mm feature and it
should be 35 mm. So, I'm going to redraw it. So,
this protrusion that you see on the left is wider
than the protrusion that you see on the left. It inferred that from the
diagram, went through that and said, "Now, this is the final
thing. I can't find any mistakes in my
operations. It looks like the right kind of
bracket. This is what it was supposed to produce on the
left. The image on the left was not given to
Codex. What it actually produced was
the one on the right. And you can see the
difference. Firstly, there is an entire bottom
portion that is missing. it should be
uh curved rather than rectangular at the bottom
left and the bottom right. At least those are the two
major errors. They're very similar but they are
not the same object. And the
interesting thing is that if you look at the uh metrics
um okay I'm going to skip all of this uh if you look at
how it decided to construct it the construction methods are
similar the original reference the object that was to have been created
started with an I boss it then we're supposed to
add a main body profile then the lower work profile and
then cut holes it cut holes codeex also cut holes
at at the end, but it started with a base roughly the equivalent of
the main body profile. Uh, and in the third
step, it cut the hole instead of right
up front. It added the circular right at the second
iteration. But what it missed was this lower fork
profile which it could not see clearly enough. But what
is more interesting is that the tests for
this that it created were insufficient as
well. And uh the final tests
I'm trying to see if I have the list of Oh yeah, further
up, right? No, where did the tests
go? Maybe this version doesn't have the
tests, but the test cases ware uh
generated by a CAD benchmark called FRECAD
where uh it provides not just the drawing but also
what is the volume of these what are
uh some of the finer details of
the shape about 40 50 parameters that you can very
granularly test along with the specification and only if it matches all of
those will we be able to say that yes this matches
What does that imply?
What I take away from these things
is number one if I give a picture to a
model and say produce something these days it is able to
produce something not only produce something it is
also able to correct mistakes in what it produces.
Second thing that I'm learning is I'm not
able to tell the difference. You already saw me reading a
chart worse than even a basic model. I've been
reading charts for decades.
This kind of a mistake is just too
easy for me to make. So I'm not very good at spotting mistakes.
Third that there are benchmarks out
there and there are ways of specifying
uh correctness out there like the CAD
bench that I can use as a format to say I will
consider this correct only if it meets all of these criteria and I
have to sit and create those criteria.
Those are three takeaways for
me in terms of how does one go about
verifying having an LM generate a visualization. In
this case, wasn't quite a visualization but close enough and I'll show you some visualization
examples. And how do you verify those? But what are your
takeaways?
now. So Anand actually we are sort of done with the
the class time. It's it's 3:15 here. We
No, it was in any case the last thing
I was going to cover. So,
yeah.
And uh for the next
session uh I would like I can assign
homework. I'll drop you an email
with some
homework. Cool. Thanks
everyone.
Okay. Just just one thing before
you leave right see he's
one person today if you're going to like pick up
uh you know top three to five people on data visualization who has been
there done hands- on stuff run a company uh sold
a company as chief of innovation at some other place and all
that it is that guy okay and many things that whatever he's
showing including the mahabharata stuff is most likely
handcoded by him. Okay. Of course, he has a team and all that. He is
extremely extremely hands-off. Extremely hands-on, right? And whatever
he showed probably generated after discussion with me just
about an hour ago or hour and a half ago. Okay? So it is
important for you to to ask the right questions or at least
questions when such resources are being uh that could be the
biggest difference between someone who comes here and physically
talks and someone whom we bring from industry that that's the biggest
difference that they could bring right because they see like lot more challenges for instance
that one example that he showed like often times people who do dashboards
are someone who doesn't know anything on the application front any of the software that you're
talking about is Why banking software took about 20 years
for them to what they are today is because it was built by someone who didn't
appreciate what finance side was anyway. So that the point is not just in
his class right in any other class where outside resources like this has
been broad you should leverage that but you are actually
going in the recursive side you know you're not even regressive side
meaning you're not you're not asking any questions and
which is not a bad thing, but at least get some
sleep during class in that case.
the I thought we got out of the call and I was giving
Okay. All right. Anyway, I didn't say
anything. I suddenly when you
Or
right. Yeah. Okay. Thank you. Thank you all.
Sure.